hello everybody
glad to be here we're by your sides
this is absolutely gorgeous all day
perfect New England weather and so part
of us is trying to get as much sunshine
through difficult as we can and look at
that and we're here to explore the topic
of human development and house coaching
and what we called tailor coaching is
might be different from what we call
regular coaching and just as a dialogue
with each other find out what we know
what my puzzles about and to start with
I'd like to each one of you introduce
yourself briefly just really very little
and what draws you to this talk about
physician synchrony I start with you
hello everybody on my call Silverstein
with the Graduate Institute where we
offer some coaching programs and
actually Suzanne and Reggie and Bonnie
have been guests faculty in our programs
at the Graduate Institute and I'm not a
coach so I didn't bring a client case
but I'm interested in coaching and how
it is integrated into theories of
development hi my name is Lily I'm not a
coach but the reasons that I'm
interested in this kind of activity is
that I I have many friends and
colleagues who are coaches and
consultants and I'm intrigued by what
they do and I also see that it would be
lovely to
a group of support a some sort of
structure of support so that we can go
out into the world and do our work while
having a base to come and have feedback
from other people and to grow to
continue to grow as the professionals
and may when we had a gathering here and
I happen to observe interaction between
Christopher Spicer and bunny and and
after that I talked to Richie and other
friends of mine and I saw that you know
what how about we just do it here so
that's not started so I want to thank
everyone he is particularly funny for
hosting this place
providing the space for us and thank you
Christopher Spicer and then take your
Ritchie for inspiring this events and
then particularly a big thing to Suzanne
you agreed to come here with us so this
will be the first of I don't know how
many more to come
or whatever this could it go I'd be
interested to explore I'm David Slade
and I have an ego and I'm hoping to
develop it and I'm interested in you
know so I'm interested from that
personal perspective like what what is
it's an interesting distinction what am
i and what is my or what is how do I
function in the world and I'm also
studying developmental coaching with
Suzanne and veena Sharma
Christopher Spicer Chris you know I'm
gonna have put intensive thought
experiment into this tipping from ego
development to ego taking apart so the
elder your thing and I don't consider
myself that elder but there I've reached
a point where there's so much cumulative
loss that you start grappling with life
differently
I work up at UMass Amherst and do
leadership communication conflict
management work with groups that in the
workplace
and I'm also developing my own coaching
and retreat business called interval
guesthouse hi I'm Bonnie and I call
myself the steward of all dolor and I
spend most my time asking but this place
wants of me so that's my relationship to
this place and one of the things I know
that it wants us to have community and
have participation and make that kind of
contribution so it's a real pleasure to
have everyone here I don't consider
myself a coach I'd be interesting to see
why I wouldn't say that
you know and so they could go that's
kind of a open question for me I would
say that I love I love to I love to
teach and I can feel that the word coach
has a boundary or parameter around it
that I don't step into so that would be
a question that I have to learn today my
name is Topher I am NOT a coach although
everyone's saying I'm not a coach
researching things I have a strong
interest in
the developments the coach the kind of
human developments and I know coach
communities and he has to do what
they're doing and I was coming to sit
and just listen on perspectives of what
two coaches run into what are some of
the that was one of the themes I
understand for today was what are some
of the difficult situations that you run
into and how do you navigate them thanks
uncle Miller and I've been a spiritual
seeker for many years and I'm now
teaching waking down a mutuality one
central concern through all of that is
ego my own of course and also how to
relate to it how did it work with it how
to think about it in a 21st century
context and I just know being with this
group of people that I can learn a lot
so I also run a mindfulness meditation
group and ego is big I mean it's always
been a big concern and it still is so
I'm just maybe I can learn more about my
own and and then how to work with others
that's out I'm echo I'm not a culture
but I have you know three months ago you
know I've been living this very you know
sort of simple life and following my
tradition which is Chan Buddhism I've
been practicing for a number of years I
only follow the one teacher so I feel
like you know life is pretty good you
know it's fine I'm satisfied with that
and then three months ago I met Bill and
then he throwing all these different
kind of approaches and different kind of
religious you know seekers and thinkers
and all that and all the sudden I feel
like wow there's some area
completely just like missing and and so
he told me about this it's gonna happen
and said you know it's a good
opportunity to come and so that's why
I'm here but I also read a little bit
about what you did and it's very very
interesting so no scientifically mapping
out what the mine is actually and and
and that's all my curiosity from that is
that yes we can scientifically making
out certain aspects of the mind but then
the nonverbal part of emotions and the
intuitions and all that how do you deal
with that part of the human capacity and
power and you know which you know you
know traditionally is the through
meditation that people get access into
those you know sort of the so called non
intellectual piece and then so that's my
that's my question here for the group
and also I'm I'm born and raised in East
and in Taiwan coming to this country
even though for number of years but um I
still feel that you know how do you
integrate this so-called traditional you
know thousands of years of traditions of
approach of tapping people is it the so
called the Buddha nature
he's mapping out as this very very you
know complicated in such sophisticated
way of tapping to the so called mind is
being there but then coming to this
Western you know fertile ground which
really you know very creative people
very in you know very um has a very
sharp roots in terms of really
understand what the mind is or what the
Buddha mind is then how do you then use
this thousand years of already developed
at the mechanism right is working right
there and then to hear people ready and
how the capacity really get into that
the minds and how do you then merge them
together
how do you then create a way of just
sort of like to make that happen here as
well so that that's my that's my
question cuz I'm I'm having uh I have a
weekly sitting in my place and and I do
monthly you know Buddhist study group so
so so the people here is it's less than
mine you know trained I just hate the
people so so I feel like I understand
them without words but but you can't
teach without words at the same time so
how do you then teach people the things
that cannot be teached by words that's
the question I feel fortunate place
right now where I get to use poetry and
code writing coaching and education in
all the things that I do among the
faculty at the Maryland University of
Integrative Health and have a health and
wellness coaching I work at Tilley OSIS
Institute which is actually about
Berkeley and we actually do training the
people or be certified as coaches given
them some additional coach training and
I'm on the phone a phone coach with
interval coach in Canada which is where
I actually got certified as a coach so
and I have coaching practice so I
actually coach real people and they pay
me which is pretty cool so what Goodbody
said is really resonates too because
they're even though coaching still kind
of belial
West in terms of a regulated industry
that there are you know where does
coaching stop and mentoring begin
teaching come in so there is a blend
there for sure I just love the way this
conversation is framed you know the
importance of ego development and our
awareness of it and tailored versus
regular coaching so I just I'm looking
forward to what this is going to go so I
really appreciate me and I just loved
how you all felt into one of those
straps one way you can say we have a
more expansive self or ego is by where
we make the boundaries as soon as you
say I'm not that you put a whole part of
the world outside of your own interior
and so it was just fascinating it's also
sometimes you think okay what somebody
says from before but it is interesting
imagine but all those distinctions we
were making between teacher mentor just
human being friend coach they're
artificial boundaries and they're there
for a good reason because we wanna have
some control over who does what and you
know it's it has become an industry so
we need some some we need some
guidelines but it's interesting when we
then identify that way I'm not that
because I don't have the credentials I
think it's what the next phrase would be
whereas we coach in for money I'm sure
each other here and there all the time
with these are all saw through it that
we take on so clearly I can do a little
bit of lecturing before we discuss the
question you raise how did the to the
eastern the Western come together we say
two things we say one Western psychology
is bottom-up and eastern side quality is
top down so you start out with the big
mind or the supreme whatever you call it
and then you think Nate more and more a
moment comes more and more gross and and
material the sword whatever terms you
use and in that I call it
we tend to start at the bottom of the
newborn child and we look at how does it
develop in all realms emotionally
cognitively behaviorally and so the to
kind of complement each other in that
way we're also talking about the
difference between growing up it which
this year is about and waking up there's
a different intent and often spiritual
teaching have to do is helping people to
wake up
not necessarily to grow up they may go
up anyway as well as part of the
learning they're doing but does these
are that these things I think they fit
each other nicely now because what was
usually lacking it in the east of
traditions was a good idea of what the
ego is it was just assumed everybody has
a healthy ego we start out there and
then we transcend it but the rough road
to how to actually develop the healthy
mature legal is what Eastern psychology
has been a lot of time now on so that's
where I come from
I was always not that I'm not interested
in the other the spiritual side but I
was interested in how do we become
adults how do we mature once we are
adults and what difference does that
make
where we are in these kinds of different
theories think you could just cut you
know the overall territory we know the
agree on the many different theories how
we divide it and what we pay particular
attention to changes there may be five
stages there may be three you know
preconventional conventional post
conventional this is just a matter of
focused on detail that we're looking at
and we find that I find that this
particular theory is a totally empirical
it's not a theory but you grew out of
data
thousands and thousands and thousands of
sentence completions just not that
somebody had an idea in or theory could
be and then you try to find data to
support it which is what how most
theories actually happened they're based
on very little data this is totally day
after day even even today but the beauty
of that is that you can find Pavin in
the data that's what anything we sort of
gasp the challenge is that of course no
data also challenges what you have
before especially when you look at the
field where people develop and then more
people developing to the later stages
then sometimes you have to say well the
see you guys have developed - that's not
a good sales point people want something
that's fixed and Static and you know
this is how it is not this is how it
looks like easy ways to develop and so
it's just interesting to me it has to be
alive but it's now the development of
the you the government is not static so
there's plenty of paradox isn't even
working with this continent and in in a
nutshell how can I say the theory is
basically one that says from when you
have the hand out here the chose the are
and there are many different ways of
showing the same material in this case
I'm showing the art because I'm thinking
life is a you know life span of whole
thing and you start out as a newborn
where you have no separation no
differentiation no words yet you have
some experiences already from your being
in the womb but you don't have any way
mom and you are just one assuming the
nipple you are one I mean there's just
you know big nipple in the sky and the
joy of being in union with that with the
source of life with that milk then you
go through this quite lengthy process of
reaching more than our culture in the
Western cultures considered and adult
Piaget was also Swiss like myself was
the first to actually look 30 in the
last century look how children develop
and said they're not just stupid
adults they're actually making sense of
things and they make sense of things by
interacting with the world and he looked
at the pattern of that so he described
this movement and then we all thought
then there's still the general knowledge
in sort of the Western world is we all
the after year about age 20 25 maybe and
then what downhill from there and only
the last when 1960s were the first ones
to say no when we actually look at the
dots
some of them develop further some get
broader perspectives than what Piaget
had us the endpoint but it's relatively
fruit few so it takes a long time to get
the data to actually show that to not
prove it in qualitative sense but to
show that is patterns and others can
understand too
so as coaches and we go over the
coaching we were saying we're helping
healthy adults function not healthy but
functional adults be even more
functional
what would therapy say what do
therapists do that's different as well
we work with non functional
non-functional as for people after
suffering we really come to the
therapist because they are confused
suffering non functioning I think that
all kinds of things that they they need
help for so in therapy you generally go
further back and you look at the origin
the causes of what's the suffering
encoding you generally look forward and
assume people have resources to
forward and occasionally of course they
did after a while I discovered is really
something that needs a deeper look and
then you might refer them to a therapist
if you're a responsible coach you
wouldn't think you can do everything and
really work on things I can do and what
identity I carry and how much
responsibility I take and how much
reward I feel myself with for being a
good teacher a good coach and all that
that is he door stuff how much am i
identified was the outcome of my
whatever I'm doing do I hold that
lightly do I see it as just sowing seeds
and they may fall wherever they fall
fallow ground beautiful or wait for
years before they come forward we don't
know and that how people will attitude
somebody has to in their craft whatever
it is that is a matter of people
development so a a an ego a person
rather may interpret post conventional
experience from a conventional
perspective and get into trouble or just
lots of trouble you know we all know
about this stuff also the spiritual kind
of trouble trying so what what we really
think is in order to transcend the ego
to go back to the eastern some general
look at things you have to have a mature
ego yes but what people often wanted a
soldier and for liberation for something
else they may have had a beautiful
moment of feeling that transcendence the
unity at the other end because it comes
back but you can with your mind and with
your experience you can tap into peak
moments you can tap into a meditative
unity
he's temporarily and then think you got
it now I'm here now I'm people
transcended when indeed you've way
nowhere near there because what we also
think and I guess it comes from I have
training as a same Magda sister so
linguist is that whatever you experience
as soon as you try to describe it that
will look that will be the way where
you're coming from so it's a this is a
powerful theory and that's why we're
using it very carefully yes so here we
start with embeddedness then we
differentiate more more MORE about three
years outlets Who am I what's me what's
not me another culture you know he's
kind of clean clean distinctions are
necessary now I
apex here and it's what the culture
supports of the culture base part that
most rewards people at the specialist
and the independent stage or sometimes
you call it expert an achiever that's
why the most rewards are and even so
there is a lot of understanding he had
incredible things created from this
perspective the whole scientific
endeavor to a large degree comes out of
that the limit is that there is not yet
an awareness of how we have been
programmed so the shift from here to
what we call post conventional food kind
of tap into that the conventional where
we live within the conventions of what's
offered in our environment that the
phosphor mentioning which looks back and
says I owe my own what I thought was the
that that truth may not be the truth yes
yeah I have a question yeah they're like
so postconventional as a society moves
right so if you have relative this kind
of understanding in schools let's say I
know that's not really true but as your
society moves does this kind of
like well that's what I'm saying yes we
know that we already have given and so
maybe 30 40 years ago when the
consciousness-raising or women and and
what is it called diversity issues came
into being that came out of this kind of
thinking we really beyond what the
culture had but now of course it's as
soon as it gets
legalized soon it becomes part of the
legal structure then it appears those
sentences those things appear much
earlier and you can no longer say that
gospel mates will be forever an index
for for school mates you know there are
long great confusion that people
especially in our community because we
interface with a lot of people that grow
up with kind of parents that have been
practicing and I've been reading and
this and that and then the children grow
up at a very young age and they appear
to be post conventional but they're not
because they're that's conventional to
their reality yes that's interesting you
can even see in different cultures where
the cultural values up though the
artfully the level I've actually tested
that was Switzerland in general in
Switzerland the values that the whole
community shares are much more like that
today here you know conserving and
recycling all those those ideas those
values but the people are not necessary
more evolved they're just having been
brought up within those values and they
hail them that the way you can tell is
the rigidity with which you hold the
value the more rigid the more attached
you are to it the less likely you are at
the flexible moment to stage there and
then there's something else happening
that's interesting
that is to me even more confusing they
where I used to work you know we had a
lot of Ecuadorians come up from down
there the legally and what they had to
go through to leave their life and come
in and establish their only businesses
and their own families it was now they
wouldn't ask cause conventional but what
we did is we went in and we worked with
them so that they had to be taught
things like that they knew more than
some of the guys that were it was a
landscaping company so some of the
people have been working there forever
Awards
typically Western conventional but these
guys even though their language skills
in their understanding of America wasn't
high there was something about their
spirit that was like post-convention on
we made them managers because they had
to understand this thing and that's a
real opportunity and think that's lost
because I don't think they would score
post conventional but there's some
there's something about them that I
don't know how to explain that you that
you experience as a type of maturity I
mean tend to use that word just clearly
as what we call everything and that
indeed if you look if you look in your
own right at that other culture you
would find we assume because that seems
to be verified worldwide universally
those Big Chief seem to be everywhere
and everything whether the cultures
collective or individualistic overall
you still see these and you can still
tell who is more mature and worse and
you just can't there may be a totally
different knowledge base it may be but
that shows up there as well
yeah I mean I totally think that would
be real
yes and the intuition about their level
of capacity and a few thought if you
test them with this instrument no they
would not I would be not the writing to
lose but like one of the tests just to
ground it was there this one man in
particular who we made manager you know
he would come in and he'd get beat up by
the guys you know like they tease them
and be rude at home and stuff and they
got
so as he gained more power he was gonna
push back until it got ugly and I had
could have a conversation with him and
says no you know look at Eric you know
what Eric is like he knew that Eric was
not smart somewhat even disabled
mentally just a guy you know and I could
tell that this guy Wilma I could see him
and I said so that's just you're Burt
you can see him that's your burden you
have to be higher and it's not like he
went higher and said oh I'm higher he
knew how to set in and make he knows he
had to make Eric feel welcome that was
just his burden even though he came on
the boat and the whole thing that was in
had that passion and shine because he
had the capacity yes the other one did
it and I knew he could see and so part
of just failed on that part of this year
is also that the lathe of the state you
really are the more responsibility you
have no less or bleaches and we say in
in Europe that you that you that's a
tenant of all developmental think that
hi you can see earlier because we have
all come through it we don't we don't
jump there are other premises we
actually go through these levels and
then we can look back and they're within
us it's like the chakras they're all
there I may actually mostly use one
level but they're present they're there
but the universe is not from some value
is that the really early stage really
has no other possibility they don't even
understand what you're talking about but
this level if you talked about
responsibility there's no time since
there's no just me surviving just me
getting to the next day just be against
the whole world other people aren't even
people in their own right there just
sources of whatever I need and so there
you can't blame them if they you know
you have to fit
find ways to interact with that person
that serves them
and so a tendency particularly in the
spiritual and the sort of early
postconventional realm is to want to
heal everything with love and
universally embrace
well guess what happens if you raise
somebody down here the ice is not the
ISIS commander needs are really on this
you can step into the good part of that
earlier power and show it your father
you're just you know hopeless so the
part of developmental retail coaching
would be too happy awareness where you
are to work on yourself
to increase your awareness primarily and
to have enough of a sensibility and an
understanding of a good theory that you
can sort of get a sense where somebody
is exclusively most people span a few
levels they don't just stay the earliest
ones just don't have any choice the more
the further up you go the more choices
you have and to get a sense of that so
that you can tailor and so what would be
the difference I mean I dream you'd
asked you in the introduction what
what's it what do you think it's a
difference between most of coaching
regular for regular coaching and
tailored coaching is there a difference
and what what if so what what would it
be
you wanna get in person discuss it for a
few minutes and then come back from see
what you came up with just to break the
pattern a little bit do you want is
really time keeper
I'm not three should I say thank you
okay if they'd like
hello
it's less and wanted to change what
they're up against there's one as we
have more actualization some my career
some I Madeline right but yeah there are
facilities are health as a truncation
awesome questions
yes
start
are you fighting feeling now soon that's
the context that we're discussing with
the question
developmental theory in your in your
background would be totally implicit
then when you have just the regular
training from a coaching school but
there many many out there that certify
you there is criteria competency which
of course if you will is already in he's
where it's coming for all the Massa as a
background so I'll jump in here so I
found I think the answer is yes if you
have a developmental framework you go
you at least have the capacity and I'm
assuming whether you have the framework
or not we're talking about confident
coaches whether they are they have this
framework or not so what a developmental
framework coach has the capacity first
of all to be aware of his or her own
worldview and personality type and a lot
of other things and with the proper
training can be aware of morale
in a very very dynamic way because we
don't assess somebody and think oh that
your that you don't lock them in
somewhere but I have I'm gonna speaking
of reference oh I have the ability to
really listen carefully to language how
the person presents what their concern
would and see developmentally where they
or she might be if I'm working with in
development to framework if I'm not
working within a developmental framework
which we might call regular coaching
let's say so and let's say I live as an
expert that's where I am in my own life
I don't know that I have a toolkit
somebody comes to me I had was a series
of toolkits and I'm gonna use my toolkit
on this client or these clients
regardless of where they might be
developmentally I'm gonna use the same
tool kit for everybody that's what I
would call regular coaching whereas I
have this slightly broader and deeper
toolkit where I can actually meet a
client where he or she is
developmentally if I'm working with in
developmental framework so I I further
humanized the client and let's objectify
him or her because I've done the same
thing for myself already yes that's
certainly one way of how we look at it
any other things yeah I think this is
somewhere and thank you for that because
I just realized something
so like there's a difference between
being a developmental coach and being a
coach that tailors from a developmental
freshman so because I think what you are
mostly saying the developmental coach is
interested in moving people development
like it come more with that country
agenda and so for me the point of this
could be a coach that tailors you need
to enter their world and see what is the
most appropriate adequate fit for them
so you know a expert we were saying I
was saying that it's lovely to work with
these people because you know they have
sometimes they just can't stick a lot of
times experts have maps
mental models of the world and they have
mapping errors and then all of a sudden
like Wow
and that doesn't and that helps them but
that doesn't that whole that whole
interaction is still in their world you
know and and so I think to tailor is be
able to enter their world and coach them
from there and sometimes people are
moving and then you know that's their
needs to move developmentally but they
stab me so y'all so listen for that
obviously is it who sponsored I mean in
the but a more corporate where people
get sent to coaching so they're
sponsored by something who are you
responsible to its to its your client
even if it means that you figure out
they should leave the job they're in or
I use you know responsible to it's the
organization who pays you for the
coaching you have to negotiate that
upfront obviously you have to be aware
that this is an issue and not blind the
fall into it and yes there's a
difference so there's plenty of schools
effective coaching out there certified
coaches who have a toolkit that they've
learned in their coaching school and
they just apply it they've applied
either as experts and don't think
earlier stages even want to be coaches
necessarily but the expert goes about
the business like that within any other
job as an expert I know what's what it
is and I'm gonna teach you I'm gonna
help you learn what I know so do these
exercises so go home and write the
reflective journal is what will happens
with an expert in the reflective journey
nothing nothing anything why it's not
really come online yet what hasn't come
online the capacity they're reflecting
yes that needs to be taught that comes
later so that you have all these things
that that people learn in their projects
also see
we are and Pekin said it most beautiful
in over the head of some of the clients
and so Taylor coaching means to be
really capable to notice what would work
with that particular person their life
circumstances they're all stare function
and what they offer you as issues that
they grab always right that's what I
said I really love them too because I
think it's actually an ethical issue to
go if you if you do have a developmental
framework to go in thinking your job is
to move somebody you or even
horizontally right but especially
vertically to think you're gonna go in
and coach somebody so they're gonna move
from expert to achieve or cheaper
somewhere else
that's an ethical that's just unethical
because we're saying people don't suffer
because they're not necessarily moving
it was a report did a study of happiness
measures and cultures around the world
and those the country and I forget which
one it is
yes happiest collective in the world but
you wouldn't say that there then they
don't even care about it I mean maybe
now they do they have computers and so
on but yeah they're not they're happy
they're not worried about developing for
developing sake is their gold they
happen recently though and I don't yeah
because they said you know when they saw
that Quebec fall they said if we don't
modernize the same things can happen to
us and they finally realize that they
want to preserve and move that this was
real this wasn't an option that was real
and it was going to come from the right
guys to their own people
so yes yeah I get what
which suggests you know the the impulse
for development is that innate or or not
I guess that's the question as well it's
both but you don't live in an isolated
flow right now
gluten is not you know no one isolated
so that's big part of the pressure how
do you define happiness but they have a
Gross National Happiness index rather
than the money index which is really in
itself a stage for kind of measure
I mean idea not a beautifully stretched
in the edges and going over there that
that's that idea you could actually
measure more of the human being than
just the money aspects of it yeah in our
culture when it's spent on therapy is a
positive thing in the sense that you
know it's income and so it makes the
economy but it could also be indicative
that you have a very unhappy population
yeah I'm getting depressed I'm realizing
as I'm sitting here that I was
conducting my meditation that in spite
of myself I'm looking at him and being
the development away of the questions
coming up in my mind is am i doing that
too much or am i doing it at the right
time like when we were talking or a
group like there's a time to go specific
and there's a time to step back in
because once you've been taught
something in a masters to get your kind
of socialized into loyalty all right yes
and then you can't ever go back
so can you go forward to beyond or have
that as part of you time I like to talk
about we have medicine bags with all our
medicines in it so you that could be
still good medicine for some people you
just need additional things in your
medicine bag transcending and including
yes thank you yeah it's not that it's
not good it's just that they tailored
would again I am now you're aware of
which of the tools practices you offer
are supporting the people in general
there's some practices meditations it's
just doesn't you don't have to even
think of development sometimes you just
can do it you can just be in that moment
and have the peace and the experience of
the expansiveness or whatever it is
you're trying to communicate across the
board doesn't matter
Ethan will take in what they play back
off and I would even venture to guess I
haven't measured it or seen the research
but I'm sure it would be that some
people at earlier stages of middle
stages have wonderful great depth in
that we practice in that kind of
transcending and then coming back and
being you know they're ordinary cells
and they're people work and more sustain
that and generally later stages do tend
to help in the sustainability of flow
states as well because he have more if
you will flexibility of control over
what's actually going on yeah yeah so
well maybe the perception is different
that you perceive things differently in
a different stage right yes you do these
are tell a different story and so that's
a piece I actually jumped over we make
them really really I think it fought the
distinction between ego and it's just
the word I mean we just don't have a
better word and I use it because before
on the Loranger my field my work use
that word right the to use took it from
you stay
the selves how you what word use is one
of those tricky things because it's a
man it's artificial choice but I say ego
is that function in us that will always
try to tell the coherent story no matter
how wacky story is from the perspective
of others you can go in and insane
enough asylum and listen to people what
they tell you about what's happening to
them and to them it will be make sense
they're trying to do the ego is doing
that storytelling the trying to put
whatever it is into this into one story
that hangs together somehow or other and
that happens from all the way from where
you as soon as you become verbal to all
the way up into the transcendent realm
because you have a story by this teacher
is your best the best possible teacher
for you you have a story by this
particular spiritual approaches superior
to this other one by these practices all
of that is still storing there's human
beings I don't think we can help it
Louis tell the story and then you can
look and that's what learn means you
started and what I continued and that
gets Teddy or Fallon now says she's
moving it even further is looking at
thousands of those stores of self
stories my experience of life in
building it on a projective test between
people can say anything they're like
they don't believe there's no right or
wrong response I don't know have you all
seen her since this completion test
maybe not everybody actually yeah it's
been a while but I just you know they're
these little sentence is raising a
family but the client or the test taker
just finishes the sentence and you have
36 different stimuli crime and
delinquency could behold that education
is my mother and I mean tapping into all
sorts of
things that are so central for most
human beings
everybody has been either a child at
some point the house children or people
they relate to us offspring so you tap
into bad things and and then you look at
those little thousands hundreds of
thousands of responses and sees there is
there a commonality of the self-identity
and the theory then maps out those
different identities that we can see
when we look at zillions of responses I
just I want to just go back a minute
maybe it's the same thing you're saying
with that our capacity to create the
narrative the story is stratus obviously
so that makes us human I guess but I'm
just struck by the way you're speaking
about how important isn't it it's what I
left there in other words wherever we're
at our own development and if we're our
own development or working with others
our independent capacity to step back
from our own experience but also a
cultural influences is really an
indication of development and
sophistication in a bigger view but it's
just an important point you know I do
think it's an important point an
important distinctions how much
awareness does the theory have about
that yes so several of the developmental
pleas are out there but they don't ever
be find what the self is just assumed I
mean you don't know what it is the
theory doesn't touch it
it's the stripes how do you think it
describes some behavioral patterns but
it doesn't say who is actually behind
all of this who does it who wants it so
yes I think that's the distinction
between ego as what we call process than
the one that that chests and then
interprets and then you know gives you a
story about what all the things they
experienced
on internal and the cabins we can see in
those stories that discussion the
theories about the cabins and that's
your transcendence include also I'm just
struck by that I mean without that
capacity functioning we have our time
transcending yet having a healthy
integration and including these steps is
in some ways a healthy way of being it
and the more unhealthy unbalanced way of
being it because how most often ego is
used in this in the sense of egoistic
selfish ego attached but that's not what
we're talking here about and that's part
of that struggle is defining the right
distinctions the right words we talked
on the way over you actually words
talked about that it comes up no matter
what you do discuss at some point become
aware of how naming whatever you're
naming is an active thing excludes other
things in that boundary thing I'm not a
cultural sponsor things outside and
wider boundary what in you needs to
define it that way but even if you say
your coach also here in the boundary yes
yes sometimes on you know their food
agreements if they're good reasons to
have those families and then there are
times when it is more healthful not to
have them or at least be aware that
that's what I am doing or that's what
I'm not sure about that but I always
wonder I think the inside is important
but it's not yet enough if you're not
plaintiff out inside of how screwed up
your and do nothing about it you know
not acting not write a new story not
write and play but just repeat the play
you've been doing on stage all along and
directed with more more character
more soft personalities and all of that
but you actually stay in the same got
the right then you play so your theory
is based on the scientific study is what
the current moment in the curve mass
right and you try to use a different way
of sit through the patterns know what's
going on then it is always just sort of
like a little step you know behind I'm
I'm probably like a worst so you just
described what's going on right now
right so then then what the sneaker is
helping the world to move because the
question it is a map that goes from the
unconscious unity to conscious unity up
here you're actually fully conscious of
how we another haven't actually talked
about what happens on this side here you
build yourself your separate powerful
self offering etc except that ourselves
I can function that can make decisions
based on information safety information
prioritizing all the things that we
think could adult you know can do but
what you don't have is with perspective
on the process of doing that here you're
starting to see mmm
so so what if if if whatever I thought I
knew and was true now I'm questioning it
now I'm realizing how many assumptions I
made that can be tested and I watch
other people good heavens you think
about it the same thing we're right here
we're seeing this microphone from
different angles me there are things
first guys those guys over there see the
blinking light as well or not is it only
on this side this either when you start
thinking about how to become furious
it's not
even my relationship initially done you
can also look how somebody holds any
theater obviously the expert Holtz is
like an expert like the truth and the
chief it may say ok this year this year
this year in this year I come there all
developmental thing I compare them and I
like this set of teachers the best and I
I this particular approach fits my needs
the base that just fits my personality
the base the way they go about it so
then you choose it then you follow that
teaching it may be a much broader kind
of teaching them down here with less
prescription and more work more in your
toolkit than done down here but it's
still fairly prescriptive like go out
and and give people a metaphor you
listen to them and then you find one
that matches them and then you give it
you give it to them rather than the
interesting question I found really
listen what kind of metaphors are moving
that person and what behind the matter
what does that actually mean to them
that particular metaphor there and I
don't know whether I'm repeating myself
but I can tell you the most powerful
experience I ever had with that was with
an approach called clean language or
symbolic modeling that I explored I was
just curious about it until the teacher
said well I can give you a free session
you can just come and experience if you
will better so I was telling them the
story of the powerful story in my life
my mother died early I have a seriously
retarded sister and all the sister and
family I would say expert helpless
father so here it is
January I stand with the grave it's
snowing it's called
and my sisters I hold her hand she's
little even so she's older and felt that
enormous burden and I felt and the way I
described it was like a millstone around
my neck I will not be able to move at my
own speed and my own interests because
now I have to take care of this father
on this retarded person and the
experience of that so I talked about
that and within an hour this whole thing
the way just us there's a set of 20
questions
the coach is completely out of the
picture there's nothing about the coach
that still is only which question when
to ask she got me to experience it as a
life west same sayshe life west and we
ended up it still moves me it was a
Hegel in one hour I said dad is Dallas
powerful coaching has nothing to do with
levels that has to do with the capacity
as a coach to completely step out of and
only be curious what's in that personal
they mean was those words he will have
an idea with millstone around you make
my team this is something entirely
different what I meant and anybody else
would mean because it was literally
something different and it's what
happened their developmental or clothing
it changed if you're really in that
sense it was transformational it changed
my relationship so that's and there's
nothing that says you can't do that kind
of work with people as well I'm giving
it as a counterexample not everything
has to be tailor coaching the powerful
approaches that are not different depend
on the level now the level of awareness
of a person to actually work with a
system like that probably has something
to it I would have a hunch that not
everybody has
transformative experience as I have it
was an easy client if you will but still
the technique itself he'll bring that
forward that transformation one of the
questions is behind this for me is how
much if has developmental coaches there
might there needs there's a need for
distinguishing between the client need
for horizontal growth versus vertical
growth right so what you experienced was
some expensiveness within your level of
development horizontally or was it I
don't even ask that question because my
theory is of my experience is that when
we help people be at home wherever they
are more at all more more fully at home
doesn't matter which level more embedded
more fitting to the environment then so
much energy gets free that they will
naturally find openings for vertical
growth then it's much easier but if you
start pulling somebody and kind of
expecting them to grow vertically when
they haven't even managed where they are
at yeah then yes then you bit my case
resistance which is an interesting word
or you will just not need it may take
many more sessions than necessary so
that's that content so you have the
innate capacity be happy
therefore he you are able to reach to
that point so in other words that that
we already neatly intrinsically happy
and at peace
somehow because of that we have that
capacity therefore you are coachable
that you're able to be brought into that
state but so let's make a distinguished
distinction between state and stages I
guess there is some you're earning I
think we all have
it has to be for happiness but for
sensing when we're unhappy maybe we
can't even name it we'll just feeling
stress sister tells us something
whatever became and define it so then
they know that to me the first question
is always how serious is that stress and
does it need more like therapy or
medical attention or is it actually
appropriate for a coaching relationship
so I'm just chatting I'm doing rationing
the quality you know that yeah what
human you know this this inequality the
innate quality I would say there is a
obviously tendency to grow certainly to
a certain level p-series say not
everybody goes beyond the middle here or
not even everybody that we just looked
at it yesterday at the conference if
they say 70% for people of any Western
Western developed countries around here
maybe 10 15 percent even earlier so we
have very few that actually are over
here and so the work we have to do is
mostly with people at these levels in
all situations and corporations
individually the sort of vegetable crowd
way where there many people
self-identify later that's a different
story
maybe there's a distinction between to
be made between the human world and the
light world I don't even know if that
means ok so it's like what your name was
was like the light world the versus
something that happens more in the human
sphere well it basically language but I
don't know I just threw it out there cuz
it was just in my head I have n you're
not trying to explore it a little more
you mean the whole ecosystem acting
include
I'm trying to nuance the quality of that
transformation without saying stated
stages and moral tale of coaching and
stuff like that like so now they have
hiss and metal right there's like but I
don't know how we try word and clean
language person I would want to know
what this actually holds some means you
just see how to do that right so I don't
know basic coaching regular coaching if
you're a good coach you know these kinds
of body language
you know this pauses you notice the
speed of how somebody talks and you try
to in some way either challenge it by
changing your speed or to match it and
the from the mental I think that's true
for all coaching the more you can match
the client both where they are
developmentally and who they are as
people what their preferences are
they're more kinetic language or more
thinking language or whether they use
more feeling language matching any one
of these items will give you great the
report and when you miss it when you
talk about thoughts when the client
concept you know just in general
approaches things more through the
feeling side that these are the skills
if they're in your bag or on also going
to be a more effective you caring coach
than when you don't have those
sensibilities and they're not
necessarily state related not
necessarily still not necessarily in one
order one would assume that truly a
mature person would have more of those
on board than somebody who's less
developed but in general these are good
things and they'll not state-related
my capacity to notice and often that's
actually interesting one of my clients I
have a very successful company in Dallas
and teach coaching the executive team
some of them and each one of the people
I have is so definitely two totally
different things with them and one of
the money spent considerable time was
just learning in in a meeting to look at
the body language of others but they're
not to show in learning to modify your
own body language invented this is not I
mean this is developmental I could help
that person become more effective but it
is not Taylor coaching it other than
that I noticed that she needed that I
guess in that sense it is and I wouldn't
talk about ta will you talk about that
just that you learn to pay attention to
this particular thing and it will make a
difference in how your meetings wrong
but it's the paying attention and that
has to do something probably with the
levels the coach how much they can pay
attention most of what's going on inside
and to what what actually happening for
the other person quit things but the
opposite happens to that because like
people whose ego development to use that
very clear phrase that are here then I
need a lot they're like starving for
that relationship so so a lot of times
they go through spiritual communities
with wonderful teachers like I happen to
think she's been young is a wonderful
teacher but he's not contract aware and
and people know I like them so they go
there and they're unsatisfied and
there's just there's a very deep
profound need to have that when you're
up here - you can't just have
transformative experience it leaves you
starving for more and for for having a
community of others who could yes it's
necessary for more it's actually you're
starving in a different way I understand
so we could you can describe the
development in anywhere
many ways you can say at earlier stages
you look for a community of like
believing of like which I say value
people who have similar values as
yourself then you could say well people
have similar cognitive capacities
like-minded then later on you even look
for life spirited people that can be
very diverse but with you really your
own force somebody who is in some
spiritual sense of a similar life we all
need that we all need I mean the phrase
are the birds of a feather flock
together it's actually deeply
descriptive of something again human
yeah yes we can be generous yes we can
be at a later stage and really really
focused and willing and happy to serve
all the labels but at some point we need
some nourishment and support as well so
the recommendation is always its own
place through the length of your art
only of esteem is statistically it gets
and not only that when we imagine growth
we you know we can any development we
can also describe the spiral the spiral
is opening up there are fewer people and
they're more ways of actually being at
these latest stages than there are of
the earlier ones so then people fall for
common and describe that loneliness you
know this kind of goes back to what you
were saying about support yes our own
development we absolutely need to
monitor the work with these two firms
working with the whole spectrum however
that's defined and then also taking care
of ourselves yes in all the way our own
developmental needs and for Silas
different some
need more of a philosophical tribe some
more of them you know what a spiritual
meditation not beyond the mind right or
whatever you know and then we all go
home for Thanksgiving dinner our
biological tribes but anyway it's great
to hear that because I was thinking
earlier about development and how there
is the bias I'm noticing in my own mind
tor I want to get out there and do it
you know but whether it's my out myself
or working with someone else I'm just
hearing the way that he first what
you're saying and how you're saying I
just feel so again it's just slow to
happen
not that I'm anyway but just listen and
development is an innate thing like
you're saying pick up and the agenda but
it's totally relax and take the time to
really get to talk to the individual and
just listener to find out who they are
that's the question who are you want to
see I say it even differently what is it
like to be you what is it like to be
that person in their shoes and with
their eyes in their environment in their
history all of that what is it like to
be you and I think one of the most
healing things for human beings is to be
listen to how few times doing it
somebody to show you listen to you yes
yes thank I found it
God I don't want to say the best
compliment but maybe is the best
compliment that I can receive as a coach
is when someone says that they felt
maybe for the first time fully seen and
heard yes if you don't forget what we
accomplished or anything else although
you know that's how to do that too but
they said they felt seen and heard
that's a big deal you know I think we
all from the other end of the I like
feeling
even heard four do we all need to mean
begin will not with the idea that were
separate individuals in the skin back
you know how how what a foolish idea
that is but here this level there is a
good sense that that soul with all the
scientific knowledge I may have that I
have more bacteria my gut and there are
stars if they're not you know it is sort
of external knowledge it doesn't
actually affect this level my sense of
self that there's no boundary just I'm
the very breath I'm exchanging with the
environment
yeah you know the separate self that was
so central to Western ideas about life
he's so limited so here starts the
boundary starts to be deconstructed so
we say this is the construction of a
separate self and this is the
deconstruction stepwise first you just
notice that the same reality can be
looked at from many different ways and
interpreted in many many different ways
that the second level of construction is
not just that there is one reality we
can look at in many many different ways
they're actually innumerable realities
because they're all based on a unique
work on the pattern of language and
using words to describe reality but
they're all individually flavored as
welcome from our history our singing so
here this is a much deeper kind of
uncertainty this we call relative
everything is relative yes but here is
even more profound there's no place to
stand on it's all the tension between I
think Pascal said it best in his own
saying is Adam in his thoughts
meditative
it's actually 1,600 or when did he leave
a while ago yeah
if teens maybe even and they were always
coffee switch well anyway the idea that
I got from him that struck me in high
school I was just dumbfounded it changed
my life I do know it's a possibility to
store it's another story that is
helpfulness on people it's fine well you
got it was like what do you say well we
have to read this stuff from Bosco say
human beings prepared to nothingness on
everything and human beings compared to
everything or the nothingness and the
teacher actually gave us the
mathematical transcription of that one
compared to zero is an infinity or
course two it's infinity on compared to
an infinity goes to it's zero as you
know mathematical thing and it
completely completely just did oh my god
yes that's the tension I feel that's
that not finding a place to stand
because I'm aware of both and so that's
a later stage kind of uncertainty and he
really and Wilbur says that well also it
doesn't often point to it is you suffer
just as much it's not that you get
happier with every level but it bothers
you list because because of what what do
people like the state just have the
early stages do not have perspective
perspective
in the resources that's not gonna deal
with you go yes more capacity to you
know honesty and straightforwardly look
at reality and that their own
shortcomings and the way the mind plays
tricks on us and accepting that we all
have biases no matter how hard we try
it's it's all of them are hardwired all
of that we're just curiosity coming
because like you can't really carry that
about you know because you have a
perspective on the unhappiness or the
sadness or the thing it becomes like
it's fascinating you know it's equally
fast in the fascination in the ah
doesn't end
so that's like a perspective on it I
don't know where you're at I don't know
where you're standing from when you have
that perspective but a kind of radical
openness I would say and finding
precisely the in-between and the tension
between the two like walking on the edge
of a salt that's where it's the most
juicy footing for truly truly curious
about what life is but to me that's what
it's like you know it's just all the
curiosity like I think there's a moment
of I might get in trouble but there's a
moment of non feet just not curious
there is no curiosity and I'm thinking
about the awareness of no self now if
there's a moment where there's just no
no no thing including curiosity but then
curiosity definitely happens but there's
a moment just before and I think also
none of what we're talking about is
about being static but it's part of a
fluid economic fluid in and out that
even states we even do my regular days
we go through States every night you go
through states this is also part of our
birth
right if you will but there is a
difference when we talk about growing up
and waking up waking up has a different
titles a different target than growing
up and I would be kind of happy can we
talk about something that oh did I
interrupt you I'm always interrupting
okay I think one of the things that I
don't know I just popped in but like one
of the things that people that I work
with have trouble with is like we've
been talking about about unity and we're
all one and and I want to overemphasize
that but then people start to get very
aware of how unique they are and at
first like for long time they might be
in these you know unique self courses or
something I think it's a really cool
idea then all of a sudden they start to
really experience I'm unique they are
well we did this in our retreat yeah and
they end up being what it hits them and
then they really cannot tease them you
know like well like well you see people
are really afraid that that most of
their experience is not shared that that
actually are they all of a sudden they
realize how unique they are the other
side of it and they get terrified right
because it's an obligation if you know
how unique your then you have to live
your unique self and that's a huge
imitation right so there's like toggle
between people just you know a lot of
people are in these communities chasing
your unique self but there's some
conventional and they're all doing the
ritual stuff and then then there's a
toggle where like thinking happen
and our retreat and people are like oh
my god do you know this but good reason
because of these want to really get it
is that is that up here somewhere that's
the no that would be anyway it's more
again more likely to happen up here
because there's more resources more
capacity to watch what's going on
but it could happen here too I mean sir
when you look at so the world of
teachings and coaching to go back to
coaching a little bit about purpose
what's your purpose down here the
purpose is usually you know what you
want to do professionally you want to
choose and later here the purpose is a
much more deeper one that is attached to
what is your unique give you that you
have been given and how are you going to
translate that in service of others and
yourself it's not either/or that's a
different kind of food Kris Ketz the
other switch that happens all your life
you realize you've taken pink and pink
and pink in the Earth's even people been
given and all of a sudden then there's a
switch right and that comes with it that
first is terrified and then you know
some of that has to do with personality
but like I said curiosity is clearly one
of the ways if you want the of the
intelligences or of different people of
different temperament some of us you and
I we know that they're talked about it
that just immensely curious and that is
probably something that compels people
more likely to it's exploring and
experimenting and asking fundamental
questions then somebody who is naturally
not so curious it's a paradox isn't it
unique in the unitive yes well there
because there are you there are things
we have all in common we all tell
stories no matter what culture what
group they're coming for we all know to
some degree we born within for life
usually let's assume we have one life
and we're gonna die the question is then
what is that which that recognize the
uniqueness what is that and is that we
all have a soul
okay where's all the self-awareness this
stepping outside of that observing isn't
that I'm just also experience to realize
where you are different in a unique
unique is an interesting way where you
are different than anybody else and what
which you can sometimes there's more
than one difference you could recognize
but what is it specifically that would
have the most impact I guess would be
the world will be the most useful and
and sometimes it's a guess you don't
know you can't know beforehand right
yeah I keep you gotta go it's almost
like I look at you you look closer and
closer and closer and you know that
eventually you see everything migrate
like you're pure spotting a spot and
you're looking deeply into it and study
and being within and eventually it
becomes like everything there's like
it's like I think about this often it
was like I can't distinguish identity
and purpose and if I go once I if I go
too much to the side and what's my
purpose then I start feeling like a
failure because Anderson Cooper tonight
interviewing me on CNN and then I
realized I've gotten away from the
questions of the self with a capital S
so I then I know I had to slow down when
I go into I'm supposed to do this but
and yet when I when things are kind of
like this and what you were doing Bonnie
but things are working that way my sense
of self and flow of purpose seems to be
effortless and not not at question
either but not always but no but that's
we call that simple kind of way it's
finished even the flow then you lose
your sense to time off you lose your
sense
set itself but that time you we also
function that are based on our training
through programs we do that's one
exercise we do is say draw what does it
look like when you're
at your face what image do you have for
that yeah and that's really tapping into
the flow what is it when and you will
again see when we do it we could do it
right now actually I'm totally lost time
so since we have any of you fun do we
have any time anybody need a bridge two
o'clock I don't know I'm not was running
this we start around three something yes
455 yes but I could imagine that
somebody might need it quick key great
let's take a break but just sure yeah
just a bio break is what they call
itself
yes see you when you're on your break us
or ask or grapple with in the next
half-hour or so just be careful what you
say because the recording still on